This, he said, contained the essential principle of animalism.
Whoever had thoroughly grasped it would be safe from human influences."
The birds at first objected, since it seemed to them that they also had two legs.
But Snowball proved to them that this was not so.
>> "A bird's wing, comrades, is an organ of propulsion and not of manipulation.
It should therefore be regarded as a leg.
The distinguishing mark of man is the hand, the instrument with which he does all his mischief."
>> The birds did not understand Snowball's long words, but they accepted his explanation,
and all the humbler animals set to work to learn the new maxim by heart.
Four legs good, two legs bad, was inscribed on the end wall of the
barn above the Seven Commandments and in bigger letters.
When they had once got it by heart, the sheep developed a great liking for this
maxim, and often, as they lay in the field, they would all start bleating:
>> "Four legs good, two legs bad! Four legs good, two legs bad!"
>> And keep it up for hours on end, never growing tired of it.
Napoleon took no interest in Snowball's committees. He said that the education
of the young was more important than anything that could be done for those
who were already grown up.
It happened that Jessie and Bluebell had both whelped soon after the hay harvest,
giving birth between them to nine sturdy puppies.
As soon as they were weaned, Napoleon took them away from their mothers,
saying that he would make himself responsible for their education.
He took them up into a loft which could only be reached by a ladder from the
harness room, and there kept them in such seclusion that the rest of the farm